Good evening everyone. Welcome to the
August 11th finance committee meeting.
Uh on our agenda, we have six new
resolutions, four new ordinances that
we're going to introduce and be speaking
and talking about tonight. So I will get
right into it. First with temporary
resolution 6725 coming through law
committee and Mrs. Kates.
>> Yes, thank you. Um, this is legislation
related to there are new settlements
related to the national opioid crisis
with various pharmaceutical companies
that the city would like to join and
this legis legislation authorizes the
administration to do that. Law director
Hall, did you want to expand upon that?
>> Um, just briefly, you probably don't
recognize the names that are included in
this settlement, and that's because they
are all uh generic um manufacturers and
distributors of opioids. Um, but that's
that's the only reason why you wouldn't
know anything about that. It's still
wrapped into the one Ohio settlement
agreement. So,
>> thank you.
>> Thanks.
>> And Mr. Bisjack will be my second and
we'll go three readings.
>> All right. Thank you. Any questions on
that one?
>> No. Temporary resolution 6825 also
coming through law committee. Mr.
Crates.
>> Yes. Thank you. Um, as a result of the
recent flooding events around the
community, there are emergency repairs
that must be made to roadways, coverts,
etc. And because of the emergency
circumstances, the city needs to go
outside of the normal bidding process to
accomplish these repairs faster for the
safety of the public. And the
legislation authorizes the city to do
that. Um, that's why we're asking for
suspension is because of the emergency
situation. Law director Hall, is there
anything you'd like to add?
>> No, ma'am. Thank you very much.
>> Um, Miss Miss B. Well, I don't know who
will be my second.
>> I mean,
>> she must be here.
>> If if she ends up not being here, I'll
just second and we'll get it done.
>> Uh, anyone have any questions on that?
>> I can just add another reason that we're
asking for suspension is uh the the EMA
is including us in their FEMA
application and part of that is us
providing a declaration. Okay,
any questions? I I do have one. Do you
have a list of does the city have or
LDOT or anyone have a list of the
damages like the roads, culverts that
need fixed?
>> Yes, I will say that we had very minimal
property damage. It was mostly parks. We
had a water main break under a bridge
from where one of our um dumpsters
decided to take a two-mile tour. uh got
stuck under a couple bridges and did
some damage underneath. Um but very
minimal property damage. Most of ours is
going to be labor from our first
responders.
>> All right. Thank you.
>> All right. Next, we have temporary
resolution 6925.
That is coming through finance and that
is myself.
All right.
That is the court that is with the
retirement of Tamor Judge Fields. Did
you want to come up and speak to that?
>> I've never passed up an opportunity to
speak about anything.
>> Um to Mayor Bartekch, longtime city
employee, uh moved to Florida, got
engaged all within like three weeks. Uh
I think we're just moving money from one
pot to the other. I just need to move it
so I can pay her out. U
yeah, she's a loss, but we we have
filled the position. I think while I was
on vacation, Jackie may have been here
and we we redesigned the position.
Before she was the director of uh
specialty dockets, which there are four
of them. Now we have just made the
position a uh grant monitor, grant
manager, grant writer, grant everything.
Uh but uh it's just moving money.
I don't know which this was just an
unanticipated I mean it wasn't something
last year during
>> I will give you a heads up at the end of
the year in my budget I will have
another probation officer that's
retiring who has 31 years in the court
38 years in peers uh Jenny Rhyr uh and
so she falls under whatever we had back
when and she's been there quite she came
in with Judge Williams in 1994
so yeah I'm just and it could be three
readings we're knows what we're doing I
just needed to move money.
>> Now I'm going to be the bad I would
rather have it passed sooner rather than
later because of her payout coming up
because she's already in Florida.
>> Yeah, she's in Florida. She moved last
two weekends ago.
>> Happy for her. Sad for us. But uh but
yeah, so we had to we're going to have
to do that payout. So it's going to
throw we're going to do that and throw
my the accounts into the red in order to
do that. So for me requesting selfish
reasons to get the account out of the
red sooner rather than later.
So you would prefer that I ask for
suspension.
>> That would be wonderful. That would be
me requesting that not the judge.
>> Oh, I would support it, but you know.
>> Okay. Any questions?
And I will ask for suspension.
And then Mr. Sully fine with me in the
second. And you got that miss. Okay.
Okay.
>> Well, you got me. Anything else? Thank
you.
All right. Thank you, sir. Uh, temporary
resolution 7025, water water pollution.
Mr. Wing is not here. No. So,
>> we have Miss Ter speak
>> maybe.
>> Denise, did you want to come up and
speak to this?
Good evening. Believe it or not, we are
about a month away from starting up the
North Water Plant. So, we're very
excited about that. But with that comes
a whole slew of things that we have to
update to come into compliance with Ohio
EPA. And one of them is our asset
management plan. Ohio EPA requires both
as part of our operating license and as
part of our loan to identify all the
assets in the system
add a condition rating and then come up
with a financial plan to replace them
and that's due within the year. So um
this will authorize service safety
director to enter into a contract with
Arcadus to update our asset management
plan
>> questions.
They're already the design consultant
for the project. Correct.
>> Correct.
>> And this was not part of their initial
agreement to do?
>> No.
>> Okay.
I mean, they're supposed to be providing
information to the IT department to be
able to put everything into their com
their uh computerized system for the
plant.
>> That's not this.
>> No, that's not this. They're working
with the IT department on the SCADA, the
plant control system,
>> right?
>> This is something entirely different and
it includes both water plants and the
distribution system.
>> Okay. focused mainly on the distribution
system, but it's part of the we have to
do it to close out the loan on the
Northwater plant.
>> Okay.
>> You want a little bit more information?
I
>> we're looking to have them do basically
a gap assessment for asset manage a gap
assessment. I'm Darren Drum. I'm the
superintendent of water.
>> Okay. Thank you. Denise drew the
legislation legislation up, but uh I had
her actually do the legislation so we
could get a contract and enter into
contract with Arcadus. Arcadus does our
modeling for our water system. We have
200 miles of water line from 4 in up to
30 in. And what they'll be doing, this
is just one part of our asset management
plan. Um
this will entail compiling all of our
assets of this is all lineal assets not
vertical. Um and it'll be used to
develop a capital improvement plan which
is part of our uh requirements through
the EPA. Uh this will uh inventory
applying likelihood of failure like she
was saying and assigning consequences
consequences of failure and establish a
final risk score. You mean so we can see
here's how old it is. Here's a failure
risk. Maybe it's older, but it's we
don't think it's going to fail. So they
help us kind of judge that and rate that
since they're doing the modeling for our
system already. Um, this score will help
us prioritize and to for a replacement
for our capital improvement projects and
will help us to to define a 20-year plan
which we can incorporate into a
five-year plan and kind of budget for
and then look as each year every five
years we usually do a rate study which
we can adjust our rates to actually meet
the systems needs. So,
>> so they're compiling a this this asset
management that they're putting plan
that they're putting together includes
all the equipment within both plants and
the exterior.
>> No, this is just exterior.
>> This is linear. You have to do vertical
and horizontal assets.
>> Okay.
>> So,
>> so is there a reason why we wouldn't put
out an RFQ on this and get a little bit
of competition if we're not if we're not
doing an asset management plan for stuff
that's within the plant that Arcade has
designed. This is outside of the plant.
Why wouldn't we put out an RFQ for this
and get a little competition? They
understand our modeling and they've kind
of designed our plan and with them
knowing our system and been working with
the city for so long, it really them
knowing it is going to be an e. We have
a lot of challenges going in the future
with the growth of economic growth in
the city and I
working with them and they know our
system it'll be a lot easier.
Yeah, they just have gotten a lot of a
lot of stuff lately without competition.
So, just raising the question.
>> So, we don't have to So, you're asking
why we're not going out to bid,
>> right?
>> Can I Yes.
>> address that. So, um Denise actually
keeps a file with qualifications in it
for qualified engineering firms for any
of the construction projects that we do.
And that is an exception to the Ohio
Revised Code requirement that we go out
for qualifications on construction
projects. And I think the main reason we
do that is because it's a significant
time savings. Um, you know, a lot of
times when we're working with moving
deadlines and, you know, the state says
we have to have something now, but we
don't know when we're going to, you
know, be able to get that. Um, I think
that's part of the reason. And I won't
say that I speak for Denise, but I think
it's, you know, why they do that in this
situation.
>> I know the county does, I mean, I've
done a lot of work for the county and
they have a $50,000 fee limit wherein
they don't have to put an RFQ out.
>> So maybe it's a different limit for the
city. I don't know.
>> Yeah, it is. We have a $77,000 cap um as
of 2025.
>> This is 100 here.
>> Yes. But regardless of the cap, the
seven the 77 is where you have to start
going out for requests for
qualifications. Mhm.
>> But there's an exception to that if you
maintain a file like I said.
>> Okay.
>> If you have an ongoing file and you keep
that updated.
>> Okay.
>> Yep.
>> Thanks.
>> Yeah. I I wondered you you've said this
is horizontal assets. Are we when are we
doing the vertical assets and when would
we get a clear picture of I mean are
they assigning a value to these assets?
>> Yes, they are. So
the m a lot of the work is the
horizontal ax the horizontal assets but
they are also doing the vertical. It's
just there's more work involved with the
horizontal because
we know what's in the plants and
obviously the new plant
um we know the condition of that and we
know the condition of south plant. So,
while a lot of the work is in the
horizontal assets, this does actually
include the vertical, which is why we're
going with Arcadus.
>> Okay, Tom,
>> I've got a couple questions. Uh, is this
part of the budget for the new plant
that you know we've
this is something you've already
allocate? You have funds?
>> Yes, this is actually ARPA funds.
>> Okay. So, this isn't new,
anything new or something additional on
top of what's already been. Okay.
>> Any other questions?
>> Last one for me. When's the last time,
how long has it been since you guys have
done an asset management plan?
>> I want to say we did a very rough one
about five years ago when Ohio EPA
requested it.
Um, so we did the very minimum and this
is actually something that is a more
valuable document to us.
>> Okay.
>> We have to do one I believe to get the
loan.
>> Okay. Um,
Mr. Wing is the sponsor, Miss Tiner is
the second and three readings is
>> three ratings is fine. Okay. All right.
Thank you.
Next is temporary resolution 7125. It's
coming through safety. Mr. Bisjack.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Chair. This is this
piece of legislation is authorizing the
service safety director to go out for
RFQS and RFPs uh for the purpose of uh
getting a professional design for engine
house 2 on the west side.
So, that is all seeking to accomplish.
Mr. Mayor, Madam SSD, am I missing
anything?
All righty.
>> I don't think that you are.
>> All righty.
>> I will just add that this is something
that council has been talking about for
several years, much much longer than me
being in this position. Uh this was part
of I think what was discussed when the
taxpayers passed the most recent levy.
Um the last two locations that the city
has tried to build on did not work out.
So we are just trying to continue that
process and we think that we are finally
at a process that's going to work. So,
mayor, anything you want to add?
>> No, other than I think we've spoke at
council and finance previously that
looking for a piece of property would
work with the planning that we have in
place for where should you locate a
firehouse. Uh we realized we already
owned that piece of land. It saves us
about a half million dollar uh million
dollars in taxpayer money because we own
that property already. There is some
issues with the property as far as we
have to raise it up and uh we are
getting some fill from the LDG property
that's essentially free of charge. We do
have to pay to transport it, but um
that's convenient also and that they
need to move dirt and we need some dirt.
But uh this is a a very good location in
a a part of the city that's currently u
underserved by fire. Uh we have our
station as uh two on the short west side
and we have nothing up north and this
allows us to serve both the west side
and the northern quarter of the city.
>> And then uh Mr. Sully will be my second.
We're going three readings on this.
Thank you, Mr. Chair.
>> Thank you.
Next is temporary resolution 7225 also
through safety. Mr. Bisjack.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chair. This
legislation appropriates $355,000
for a new medic that was ordered back in
2023. Uh initially when this order was
placed, funds were not initially
encumbered. Uh these funds, however, are
coming from fire impact fees, the fire
impact fund to be more specific. Uh so,
Council Member Tiner will be my second.
We will be going for suspension. Mr.
Mayor, Madame SSD, Chief Schultz,
anything else I'm missing on that one?
Just making sure. No. No. All right. So,
that's that's all I've got for that.
Thank you.
>> You guys have any questions? Do you want
Chief to come up or we holding off on
that?
>> Holding off.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay.
>> All right. So, we are going to have a
bigger conversation during the regular
meeting. Um, and we'll go from there.
All right. That is it for resolutions,
ordinances. is the first new ordinance
is 3625 coming through code enforcement
and zoning. Mr. Sully,
>> uh this uh legislation is to create a
new uh position for zoning inspector and
I'm going to defer to uh
the administration here to explain what
we're doing. How's that?
>> Sounds great. Thank you. So, if you all
recall, we had a zoning administrator
that retired earlier this year in March,
and it was the administration's request
that um the new planning zoning
department try and get through the
summer to see how necessary that second
zoning inspector was. Um they are
falling very far behind in their zoning
inspections and trying to keep up with
complaints and compliance.
In the meantime, we have another
position in the city um that's kind of
underutilized and in working with the
other department head, they feel that we
could move that individual from one
department to the other without
the first department
suffering any consequences.
um the in that individual that we want
to move over uh actually has some
experience doing some zoning inspections
was starting to train in this um pri
several years ago prior to uh
Pete retiring. So we feel like this is a
good fit, a better use of our resources
without having to add bodies to the
city's payroll. Um we feel like this is
a really good move for the city and for
the employees. And with that, I'll if
the mayor wants to add anything or I'm
open to any questions.
>> The key takeaway is that we are
abolishing a position in one department
and moving that person to another
department.
So, it's no additional um people on the
city staff.
>> But the way our zoning our ordinances
work, we have to go before council
because it only allowed us to have that
title for one person in the department.
So, we can't just move people without
coming to council.
>> The other important thing is uh there's
money in the budget currently in
planning and zoning to cover this uh
position.
>> So, we're not we're not asking for
additional money either.
>> That's a really good point. Thanks,
Mayor.
>> Sorry, I'm messing up my notes over
here. Questions?
>> Yeah, I this is a very much needed
position. I really thank you for doing
that because I've even voiced that to
you guys that because Andrew's got a lot
of work to do. And so, how soon will
they be allowed to start?
>> As soon as we pass the ordinance and I
think that we have it in for two
readings so that everyone has plenty of
time to ask questions and the public's
has plenty of time to be aware and we
and I think that I think Chasen Carter's
here, the director of the department,
but she was comfortable with that. she's
trying she's been trying to help it jump
in and help with zoning inspections with
Andrew and there's another person um
that's been trying to help in when they
can but it's it's a lot.
>> It is a lot for
>> So the goal would be to have um the
other employee transferred over there by
the end of September to really help.
Thank you for doing that.
>> Any other questions, Mr. Sully?
>> Two two readings.
>> Okay. with Miss Tiner is your sec. No,
I'm sorry. Mr. Luxembourg is your
second. See, I'm still messing up my
notes.
All right. Uh, temporary ordinance 3725
coming through public works. Miss Tiner.
>> Yes. I'm going to have Kirk come up and
talk about this is about the U school in
Arbor Valley Drive.
Trying to finish up some things.
>> Good evening. Um, Harbor Arbor Valley
Drive was originally constructed
um as a private drive with the school
and I think back in the 80s it was uh
the city accepted it as a public roadway
and it is a public roadway today. The uh
in the meantime with the schools opening
up next year we are doing um
improvements including some alignment
changes along Arbor Valley. So, what
we're trying to do here is vacate the
old roadway slash ride ofway and replace
it with a new ride ofway that's going to
be u align better with what we're doing
out there. Frankly, the old ride ofway
didn't really even follow the old road.
So, this is a a cleanup thing. We're
going to vacate it and dedicate it and
then um it'll match what we're doing
with our new roadway out there.
Any questions?
>> Mr. Als would be my second.
>> All right. So, we're doing three
readings with Mr. Als is your second.
All right. Thank you, Kurt.
>> Thanks, Kurt.
>> Temporary ordinance 3825 coming through
the law committee. Miss Kates.
>> Yes. Thank you. Uh, this legislation is
to add a prohibition for camping on
public and private property within the
city. Law Director Hall, would you like
to give us an overview of that?
>> Sure. So, um, law committee had been
discussing this for some time. Um,
downtown particularly, we were having
trouble with folks camping on public and
private property. Um, we've always had
trouble with uh, folks camping under
bridges. Specifically, code enforcement
has to go out uh, every Thursday and do
a cleanup under all of our bridges
during the summer. Um, but we were
noticing it more in terms of the city
administration and then we were
receiving more complaints with regard to
folks trying to use our public spaces
and and being inhibited or or prohibited
from doing that by um individuals who
were residing in some of those public
and private spaces that they weren't
supposed to. Uh, and so this is the the
language that we came up with. Um, and
the goal is not to penalize, you know,
anybody who finds themsself unhoused,
um, but rather to give code enforcement
and law enforcement a way to move them
on, um, from that property so that
everybody can enjoy those those public
spaces um, and their own private spaces
um, safely and without concern about,
you know, coming across, you know, human
waste, um, animal waste, drug
paraphernalia, you things like that that
that are often found unfortunately at
these these so-called camping sites. Um
so a first violation is a minor
misdemeanor. Um it's not punishable by
jail. Uh additional violations could be
punishable by jail. They would be
enhanced if it was within a one-year
period. Um but I think it's important to
note that the the intent behind this is
not to again, you know, put anybody in
jail for being homeless. um you know,
code enforcement generally takes a uh
Lutheran Social Services employee out
with them in order to try and help
people, you know, get moved on. Um I
know from my experience with the police
department, they it's, you know, it's a
last resort for them to arrest somebody
who's refusing to move on from public or
private property. Um you know, the goal
is always to just get folks to take
their belongings and and try and find
shelter. um when they can. So again,
it's this was asked for repeatedly. Um I
had complaints to my office. I know the
mayor had complaints to his office. I
know the the police department and code
enforcement are dealing with this on a
regular basis. Um and so this was the
language we came up with to try and help
uh you know alleviate those issues.
>> Thank you, law director.
>> Yes, ma'am. This will go three readings
and Miss Bitler will be my second.
>> Okay. Anyone have any questions on that?
>> Yeah.
>> Yes. Mr. Wing,
>> uh, law director, does this does this
impact, uh, lawful camping in someone's
backyard, for example?
>> So, generally, um, all of our, uh,
enforcement is complaint driven, right?
So, we don't anticipate that anybody is
going to be complaining about, you know,
the local boy scouts who want to get a
camping badge and, you know, go out in
the back backyard and set up a tent. Um,
this is more the goal is to make sure
that you know somebody's not in the bank
parking lot, somebody's not in the
church steps, that kind of thing. So,
it's it's generally going to be um
enforced when there is a complaint just
like our parking is right now.
Essentially, we don't generally enforce
parking unless it's causing an issue in
the neighborhood. Um, and then
absolutely we we do that because it's,
you know, it's a service and safety
issue. Um, but we also there's a
provision in there that allows the
service safety director to uh permit
camping. So the the parks have the
ability to permit camping in the parks
at any point. The park board and and
superintendent can make that decision.
Um, if if there was to be, I don't know,
the the Native American group, for
example, I think they do it at the
fairgrounds now, but they used to do it
at Alley Park. And so they would stay
in, you know, reconstructed um teepeees
essentially at times. Um, so you know,
that kind of thing could be brought to
the service safety director if somebody
was trying to do something for an
extended period of time or, you know,
anything that would be out of out of the
norm that might draw some attention and
and need some permission in advance, I
guess.
>> Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
>> Okay, Mr. Sk.
>> Yes. May I law director Hall? Would it
be fair to say that I mean we we do have
a trespass law on the books,
>> but that would be a more severe penalty
if it was enforced against somebody who
would be let's say trespassing on
private property and therefore this
would be a more humane approach because
it's a lesser kind of a penalty
involved. Is that correct?
>> Yeah, absolutely. You're right. So
criminal trespass is automatically a
misdemeanor of the fourth degree. So, if
you have to be arrested for criminal
trespass, that's automatically a
potentially jailable offense. And
typically, the courts are going to give
somebody who engages in that kind of
behavior, probation as well, because
they're going to try and make sure that
that person doesn't go back to that
property. Um, so this is just a
citation. Um, it's not, you know, full
on, you know, go through the entire
criminal justice process. So, yes,
you're correct.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Any other questions, Miss
Bitler?
>> Uh, thank you. Just one quick question.
Um, so, uh, under um 568.02
subsection A1, um, we are defining
camping. Um, that includes use of
personal or private property. One, help
me understand storing personal property.
um not being allowed, especially as that
would relate to a man-made structure.
So, can I put a shed out in the backyard
and store my lawn mower in it? And that
would not be considered camping.
>> No, that's not considered camping
because you for a shed, you have to have
a permit.
>> Okay.
>> So, it's got to be a permitted use. Yes,
ma'am.
>> Thank you.
>> Yep.
>> All right. Any other questions on that
one? All right. Temporary ordinance
3925. This is also coming through law
committee at sponsor on this one is Mr.
Bisjack.
>> Uh thank you Mr. Chair. Uh this piece of
legislation is seeking to establish a
franchise agreement with South Central
Power uh for a period of 25 years. Uh
essentially this agreement mirrors the
similar agreement we've had for the
previous period. However, the one big
difference was that there's to be a
review period by council every fifth
year uh just to see uh work with South
Central Power, see if there's any reason
to change the agreement. Um you know,
depending on economic factors, uh other
external factors that maybe can't be uh
expected at this moment in time. So
that's that's what the legislation is
seeking to accomplish. Mr. Skoonover,
you're my second. We're looking to go
three readings. Mr. Mayor, if you have
anything more to add to this. So most of
you know that we introduced uh similar
language uh in November of last year and
through went through the process and was
tabled for a long period of time. Uh
South Central Power and uh the city had
discussions along the way and uh
essentially an agreement could not be
reached between the city and South
Central. We presented our legislation
and council voted no on that
legislation.
Uh last week myself and uh Director
Woody met with uh Rick Lemons, the CEO
of South Central Power uh showed him
this legislation, discussed it with him.
Um he's not necessarily satisfied with
the information with the the way the
ordinance is structured. Uh they want
exclusive rights to their territory as
mentioned previously. Uh however, we
have no franchise agreement with South
Central Power currently and they operate
within the city. They're doing work
within the city uh to fix outages and
replace service and uh I think both
parties agreed that a franchise
agreement was beneficial to each the
city and South Central. Um during the
discussion uh we discussed as a group um
we're in no critical hurry to pass this
legislation even though we agree it
should be passed in in place u for the
benefit of both parties. Uh Mr. Lemons
uh proposed for the first time uh
language that might might be beneficial
to the city and South Central that might
help them come on board with supporting
the legislation. We have not seen that
language. I can't say that it is exactly
what we want or would we would agree to,
but I think they are uh South Central
was a major contributor to the economy
of of Fairfield County and the city of
Lancaster. They've been longtime
partners and um I did advise him that we
would be anxious to see what he proposes
and uh that we would review it and have
an open mind and uh address it once it
is presented to us. So I do expect
something to come from South Central
Power. I I'll present it to the law
director. We'll discuss it and we'll see
if it's something we can work with and
if it is, we can amend this legislation,
uh put it before counsel and move
forward. If it's not something we live
with, you know, we'll ask council to
consider the new changes, the five-year
review as an opportunity to revisit this
down the road in 5 years instead of 25.
We also removed the automatic renewal
period. At the end of 25 years, this
legislation was set to renew for another
25. That has been removed. Uh we think
that's beneficial or helpful for South
South Central's position. So that's
where we're at. This is first reading.
We're proposing three readings and I
might even ask you to table it should
that be necessary.
But uh we're trying to resolve an issue
that has lasted for way too long.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Questions?
>> No, I I have one. Um,
so if there's a potent I mean
if there's a potential that they're that
yeah, we can change it, but if we think
that's going to potentially happen, why
are we introducing it? Because then it
could sit on the table for another six
months like it did previously, right?
>> Well, we amen language and uh ordinances
and resolutions
uh periodically throughout the year.
>> Yeah. Uh, we moved this forward because
there was no movement from the South
Central Power side, but in fairness, I
felt I should meet with Mr. Lemons and
and advise him we were moving this
forward, and that's why it's in front of
you today. Um, we have a table for a
reason. If we decide to table it, we can
we can table it.
>> Okay,
any other questions?
>> Yes,
>> I'll just add to what the mayor had
discussed. We also were very clear about
the timeline of the three readings for
South Central that if they did want to
propose language, this is the time frame
that they would have to propose the
language. So if they propose it would be
within that time frame. If they don't
propose any additional language, then we
would just proceed as normal.
>> Okay.
>> I expect something this week. Uh that's
kind of the timeline he agreed to.
>> Okay. Any other questions?
Any other ordinances or resolutions
we're going to introduce?
I am up for department updates if we
have anyone wanting to give a department
update.
Chief Snider.
>> Thank you, members of council. I'll be
brief. I know we're running a little bit
long. Um, wanted to take a minute to
recognize a few members of the agency
for uh their work on lessening a uh
financial impact to the city. Deputy
Chief Kaitton, Lieutenant Ree, and uh
Lieutenant Underwood all worked towards
a grant through OCJS uh through a local
franchisee to help replace
defibrillators or AEDs in our fleet. Uh
to give you some backstory, our entire
fleet of cruisers is outfitted with AD
defibrills or these are electronic
devices that help uh intervene in a
cardiac event. and they have reached the
end of their useful life probably over
the last couple of years where the
batteries are going out and the
equipment just isn't functioning
correctly. So, we do cost-saving
analysis to see how we can get things in
the PD. Uh, obviously lessening trying
to lessen the burden to the to the
taxpayer. Um, and those three
individuals reached out to OCJS,
identified a grant that they co-wrote
with OCJS, and there's a very high
likelihood that we'll receive $45,000
uh through this franchisee grant to
replace the fleet of AEDs. And just to
give you some uh context, in the last 30
days alone, we responded to three
cardiac events that involved AEDs. One
where the AED was effective, one where
the AD was not effective, and one uh
where we tried to use the AED and it
just was not in working order. So, we do
utilize these quite a bit. If we are
successful, I can't promise anything. Uh
that would likely be $45,000 cash flow.
That's a no match grant. No other uh
contingencies for the city to replace
all of our ads in the cruiser. And
that's as a direct result of those three
individuals taking the initiative to do
that. So, I just wanted to recognize
them publicly for that. That's all.
>> Thank you.
actually
>> that strikes home. My former baiff two
weeks ago had a cardiac event after
running. He run he runs every morning.
Don't run. It almost killed him. Uh but
your officers came upon him. Uh he was
cold to the touch, blue lipped, used the
AEDs on him, brought him back to life.
He's still with us today. Uh I wasn't
planning on saying, but the AEDs were
Yeah. and uh because he was it was a
Sunday morning over near the high school
and he was in his car and they responded
immediately. Three officers uh they used
the AED they brought him back to life
and he's still with us today. So I
greatly appreciate it.
>> Thank you.
>> Questions?
>> Anyone else?
Chief Schultz, could I ask you to come
up and give an update on the uh water
rescues?
>> I'm sorry, Justin. I didn't see you
coming.
>> Thank you. Good evening, everyone. Um a
brief update. Um there was a lot of
activity a couple weeks ago as
everybody's seen the news. There was um
some flash flooding events that greatly
impacted uh the citizens of Lancaster
Langster Festival. Um throughout those
two days, the Langster firefighters
responded to multiple incidents. Um we
were able to uh rescue um overund8
people, 110 people and roughly 40
animals. I think they counted 38 dogs
and two cats. Um so it was a very
successful event for us. Um nobody was
injured, nobody got killed. Um and it
was a great um opportunity for us to see
all of our local responders working
together so well. the Langster Police
Department, LDOT, gas, water, um other
mutual aid companies from other fire
departments, uh the dive teams, and when
we need when we were in a moment of
need, everybody came together to make
sure that we would take care of our
community.
>> Thank you.
>> Question.
>> How many people How many people did you
have to use from the fire department to
do that? So on the day of this most
significant flooding, uh we responded to
over 40 calls. Um we had a slightly
shortened staff of 16 firefighters,
excuse me, 17 firefighters. Um as we saw
the opportunity for the incidents to
continue to escalate. Um we did an
emergency call in. Um we called in
another 16 firefighters to back fill. Um
they were in those suits doing rescues
for um multiple incidents have really
worn out. So, um getting them in there
in case there' be more incidents happen
as well as give those um responders who
are already on duty a chance to take a
break, get the suits off, get cleaned
up, um was a a great benefit to them. Um
but for the most part, the the overtime
personnel that we had coming in for that
event um were on duty less than four
hours.
>> So, we're fortunate we didn't need them
any longer than that.
>> That wasn't the length of time was, but
I just wanted to make sure had enough
personnel to help for that.
>> Yes, we did.
>> Any other questions for Chief?
>> No.
>> All right. Thank you.
>> I think it's the best for last now.
>> Good evening. For those that don't know
me, my name is Justin Chandler. I'm the
assistant IT director for the city of
Langster. Uh SSD Woody asked me to talk
about No Before tonight. So, no before
is a cyber security awareness training
and fishing simulation online platform.
Um, we've been using that for the last
couple months. Um, I would say we're
probably about 90% of our uh office
personnel is
trained per se. Our our initial our
initial goal was to get everybody like a
a generic 30 minute training on on
fishing attacks. So, we still have about
10% left. At some point, I'd like to
visit the uh the the other departments
individually and provide an on-site
30-minute training for their nonoffice
personnel. Uh I just have not had a
chance to do that yet based on other
projects and such. In addition to the
training, um
we have the ability to send out
simulated fishing tests. Um, so we we
keep track of who has been
uh fishing simulated and and and I've
been trying to work with each department
for um repeat offenders to to try to get
additional training for those users. So
that's something we're kind of excited
about. Um cyber security is something
that we really have to pay attention to
going forward especially with the new um
mandates from the state and we just have
to always stay ahead of the game.
So any any questions on on that?
>> Any questions?
>> How did council do? Did they all take
the training?
>> No.
>> Okay. All right. Thank you.
>> I I would say
>> I just want you
>> Yeah, give us a number. We want to hear
>> um seven of you have not taken the
training.
>> Okay, ladies and gentlemen, if you
>> one of you failed a test.
>> Oh, so all right. One of us, one one
failed it as well. So ladies and
gentlemen, if you do have an
opportunity, please take the training. I
typically have to take it from other
people as well. So anyway,
>> did I miss an email? Like I was trying
to avoid emails and I missed it cuz I
initially thought you were talking about
like fishing. There have been people
that said, you know, I just saw it and I
didn't know what it was. So again, there
there you should have an email in your
inbox
>> from no before that says you've been
enrolled in training. If you do not see
that, uh, call me and let me know and
we'll get you set up.
>> Okay.
>> I have a quick question.
>> I didn't ignore it. I just
>> No, you're good. Go ahead.
>> Quick question on those fishing emails.
Since you're sending out simulated or
emails, are we supposed to do the report
to fishing or can we just delete that?
>> Yes. I'm glad you brought that up. So,
I'm not sure why it doesn't show up in
all versions of Outlook. Um, but no
before does have like a little fish hook
icon. Um, if you see something fishing,
whether it's from me or you think it's
an actual legit one, just click the
button. Um, if it is from me, it'll come
up and say, "Congratulations, you pass
the test." If it is not from me, then
you'll get a thank you for reporting.
So, I don't know what I'm sending out.
That's all controlled through the the
app. So, a lot of people send me some
stuff and they're like, "Is this from
you?" And I'm like, "I I don't know. I
don't have any control. I just tell it
random stuff and
it's probably best that I don't know."
Okay.
Any other questions?
>> No.
>> All right. Thank you. Thank you.
>> Anyone else for departmental updates?
Seeing none, I will defer Mr. Porter for
meeting prep.
Thank you very much. This evening we
have one special presentation from the
chief who has already figured heavily in
the uh discussion this evening. So
that'll be at the beginning of the
meeting. Um and one new um note for the
meeting is that during new business we
will do be doing committee updates from
our council committee chairs just to
give us a heads up on any potential new
legislation that may be coming down the
pike.
Okay.
Any other discussion items for finance?
Seeing none, I will take a motion to
adjurnn.
>> Motion to adjurnn.
>> So moved.
>> Second. All right. We are adjourned at
6:44.
>> Um the regular meeting of Lancaster City
Council will convene at 6:55.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 74-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
>> Hi, this is Jill Henwood with the
Victoria Players Children's Theater in
Baltimore. We are currently in our
eighth season thanks to local support.
This month, we are really excited to be
chosen as a recipient of the Buckeye
Cares program. That means Buckeye will
make a generous donation to help our
efforts with every vehicle they sell
this month. From all of us at Victoria
Players Children's Theater, we say thank
you, Buckeye.
Please rise if you're able and join me
In a moment of prayer,
God grant us the serenity to accept the
things we cannot change, the courage to
change the things we can, and finally,
the wisdom to know the difference.
I'd like everybody to please join us in
the pledge of allegiance. At this time,
we're going to have some special guests
come forward to lead us in the pledge of
allegiance. We have Michael, Andrew, and
Edward with Troop 106. Gentlemen,
>> to the flag of the United States of
America and to the republic for which it
stands, one nation under God,
indivisible, with liberty and justice
for all.
>> Thank you guys. We appreciate it.
I will now call to order the August
11th, 2025 Lancaster City Council
meeting. Could we please call the role?
>> Mr. Als
>> here,
>> Mrs. Bler
>> Mr. Bisjack
>> here,
>> Mrs. K
>> Mrs. Hoop
>> here,
>> Mr. Luenberg
>> Mr. Skunover
>> here,
>> Mr. Sullie
>> Miss Teener here, and Mr. Wing
>> here. Let the record reflect that all 10
members of Lancaster City Council are
present this evening. At this time, I
would like to take a moment and welcome
our newest council member, uh, Kathy
Bitler. She is not necessarily new. She
has served before. Uh, Kathy, would you
like to introduce yourself?
>> Uh, thank you, um, Mr. President. Yes,
my name is Kathy Bitler. I served as
president of city council in 2014 and
15. Um, retired and, uh, living the good
life here in Lancaster. Happy to be part
of the organization again.
>> Thank you, Council Member Bitler.
Okay, we will go now to the reading and
disposing of the journal.
>> I have regular meeting minutes dated
July 14th, 2025.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the journal. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign. Now
move to the reports of city officials.
>> I have eight of them. Um, email data
July 15, 2025 regarding NOEC rate
increase submitted by law director
Stephanie Hall. Email data July 18, 2025
regarding city hall July progress update
submitted by facilities manager Eric
Nolan. Email dated July 21st, 2025
regarding a notice of the road closures
to East Main Street submitted by storm
water manager Steven Walstead. Email
dated July 28, 2025 regarding a new
domain name submitted by information
technology director Mark Star. Email
dated dated sorry um July 30th, 2025
regarding August 14th planning
commission submitted by city planner
Traine Carter. Email dated July 31st,
2025 regarding an update from storm
water department on the July 26th and 27
storms submitted by storm water manager
Steven Wilston. Email dated August 4th,
2025 regarding an invitation to safety
committee meeting um submitted by
council member Mr. Bisjack. And lastly,
a series of emails dated August 8th,
2025 regarding economic development
updates on the TIFFs uh submitted by Pro
Council President Porter.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials.
>> Second. We
>> have a motion and second to receive and
file the reports of city officials. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We now
move to communications.
>> I have six of them. Email dated July 17,
2025 for Powersfront annexation
corrections submitted by Zachary Walker
with plank law form LPA.
Series of emails dated July 17th through
the 21st, 2025 regarding immediate
action required on Brookdale subdivision
flood crisis submitted by Megan Miller,
a citizen of Lancaster. Email dated July
20th, 2025 regarding technology, rape
and human trafficking. Uh submitted by a
human rights activist Andrew Lynn
is Escordo.
Um email dated July 25th, 2025 regarding
economic development updates submitted
by Stephanie Bosow of the Lancaster Port
Authority.
Mail received August 1st, 2025 with
Rooers liquor license permit 07511421-1
submitted by the Ohio Ohio Department of
Commerce, Division of Liquor Control.
Email dated August 1st, 2025 regarding
Ohio's residential consumers. Submitted
by Katherine Mets of Ohio Consumers
Councils.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the communications.
>> Second. We have a motion, a second to
receive and file the communications. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. At this
point in the meeting, we do have a
special presentation from Chief Schulz.
Um, this is in relation to tonight's
piece of legislation specifically
related to
um
>> 7225.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Council Member
Bisjack. 7225, the emergency piece of
legislation regarding the medic.
>> Good evening, members of council. Um, as
the president stated,
there's a piece of legislation brought
forward by the fire department tonight
um that I anticipate um possibly a
spirited discussion about. Um so I've
been allotted some time to go over the
issue um and answer any questions that
you might have. Um in 2022
we had gone through the process of
ordering two medics. It was right after
COVID. Um there was a a high demand and
low supply. Um it was discussed in a
couple of the safety committee meetings.
At the end of 2022, in the beginning of
2023, um the need to replace yet another
medic for the Langster Fire Department.
Um, a sales agreement was signed on
March the 1st of 2023
um to purchase a medic unit with a lead
time of 800 days. It's actually went
over 900 um for sale price of 353,000.
Um it was communicated through the
safety committee at that time. Um money
was not encumbered in 23 um and nor was
it in 24 and much to my surprise it was
not encumbered for the 2025 budget in
the year in which we were expected to
take delivery. Um the issue came to my
attention a couple weeks ago u meeting
one of the battalion chiefs discussing
the final delivery of the truck. Um I
was able to to share some pictures of
the last safety committee. Um it is
nearing completion. Langster Fire, all
of our specs uh customuilt unit um that
we anticipate to take final inspection
and delivery of next Thursday. Um
pending the outcome of the legislation
tonight. Um the request is to move
355,000 from the fire impact fee um
which the auditor was able to verify for
me has um sufficient cash balance to
cover the entire expense um and do this
in one reading for the timing of being
able to pick up the medic and and take
the final delivery um at the anticipated
date. So that is the best way I can kind
of summarize the issue. Um, I'd be happy
to take questions now if that's okay,
Mr. President.
>> Yeah, we can we can open it up for
questions. Um, and we'll start. Who has
some who who has some inquiry for the
chief regarding this particular issue?
>> Excuse me.
>> You do.
>> Okay. Council member K.
>> Um, Chief Schultz, so
it would the money was not encumbered,
but we signed a contract in 2023. Does
that mean that the legislation did not
go through council to approve it?
>> To my knowledge, there was not
legislation done at the time of the
sales order sales agreement being
signed. No.
>> And do we have any legislation for that?
Now, before tonight, that's what this is
tonight, right? Th
>> this tonight is to um appropriate the
monies that we have now to pay for a
bill that we had then is the way it's
explained to me. Um, I'm still learning
the nuances of city government and I
appreciate everybody's patience. Um, but
no, there wasn't legislation to do a a
purchase. Um, I don't know if that was
normal or not for purchases like these.
Um, the ones I have been part of um,
since filling this role as the chief of
the department is legislation, money,
and we purchased the fire truck. Um it
it's just a little different situation
that I'm not familiar with, but I'm I'm
learning as I go along.
>> Um Law Director Hall, are we is the city
obligated to this contract?
>> So, I've read the contract and Chief
Mafen signed the contract um
representing that he had the authority
to do that. Technically, he did not. So,
and he never had um the service safety
director sign the contract, which
obviously wouldn't have been SSD Woody
at the time. It would have been Paul
Martin. Um nor did he provide the
contract to my office for review and uh
approval. Um so therefore, technically
we are not um not obligated to take the
medic. Um but obviously, you know, there
could be some some ramifications for us
legally that I'd prefer not to go into
as a result of not doing that.
>> Okay. I have one more question if I may.
>> Yes.
>> Um, Mayor McDaniel, this obviously
didn't go through the normal process of
approval. So, I would like to know from
the mayor's office, not tonight, but
eventually I would like to know what
we're doing to prevent this from
happening again.
>> Uh, great question. And I've actually
probably got additional explanation
beyond uh, Chief Schultz. So, try to
figure out how this happened. Again,
none of us were in our current roles
when this happened. This came before
November 14th of uh 2022. The safety
committee heard from uh Chief Mafen
about this purchase specifically and it
was discussed. Um and then again on
March 13th, he announced that the
purchase the contract had been signed.
Um, so I actually went and started
reviewing uh minutes from council
meetings and I discovered uh the video
of a presentation made by uh Chief Mafin
on February 27th to city council where
he announces that um
discussing the replacement of medic one
and that it will be available uh it will
not be available till 2025. So, I
decided to pull the video up and watch
it. And explained by the chief at the
podium was that he was prepared to uh
initiate a contract for medic one, which
is this is the medic that's coming in
now, and that the money was in his
budget for 2023. So, there's two ways
that council authorizes purchases. One's
through the budgeting process. The
other, as I as explained by Chief
Schultz, is when you have a purchase,
um, it comes before council, money's
appropriated, etc., etc. Long story
short, the money was not in the budget.
Why do I think he said that? Because in
the budget was $563,829
for the purchase of medics.
Well, we bought two in 2023 and that
money was spent on um I'm not sure what
designation they have, but on two medics
that we received in 2023. However, when
he spoke at the podium, I believe that
he felt he had the money to purchase
medic one.
That money was spent. He had a zero
balance at the end of 23 and no one at
the administration
or the fire department level noticed
that discrepancy.
Um, as far as what we're going to do to
make sure it doesn't happen again, uh,
Chief Schultz and myself and Director
Woody have went through the fire
department budget. Chief Schultz Schultz
went line by line recently
um looking at any issues that might be
there and we do not believe there's any
issues or concerns and as far as policy
we're going to uh make sure department
heads and and as a matter of fact I
believe at the last department head
meeting last week you emphasized the
process and that it must be done
appropriately.
But with that said we're not done with
this topic yet. I believe the research
indicates what happened. It doesn't
justify the mistake, but it does to me
show how it may have happened. Um,
I know that when uh Chief Schulz reached
out to Chief Mafin, Chief Mafin was
confident that he had a a PO. However,
that was three years ago and there's a
lot of government purchases made by the
fire department along the way. He may
have been thinking of something else,
but there was no PO. There was no
authorizing legislation.
The only way to fix it now is with a
then and now in front of council
tonight. And as the law director
mentioned,
there could be ramifications if we
choose not to do it. But I would say we
need the medic. We expect expected the
medic. Uh it will be replacing a 2008 or
20 2016
>> 2016
>> which will revert to a backup rule. So,
we fully anticipated this medic coming
in. Um,
again, in the transition uh at the fire
department and through the
administration,
you know, I think we assumed it should
have been done correctly and I I think
the auditor would agree that uh this was
not discovered by us until we found out
that it this issue existed. The only way
I know to fix it is for council, if you
choose, to pass it then and now and
allow us to purchase the vehicle. and
understanding that it was fully planned
for. Council knew about it through the
committee process and through finance
committee meetings right here at this
podium. Uh the money that we planned on
spending for this medic was fire impact
money and that fire impact money is
sitting there uh able and ready to pay
for this expenditure.
So that's my explanation. I'll be happy
to address any questions anybody might
have.
>> Thank you, Council Member Ter. So yeah,
I got we got the money, but it's the
process of how it was done, you know,
and that's why everybody, you know, I'm
very meticulous of, you know, making
people accountable in that. And so you
said there was a zero balance and nobody
caught it. Um Trisha, you always say you
hold everybody's feet to the fire.
>> As for the budgets that were set in
there, the five were for two previous
medics that came before city council
that I have legislation for. The
ordering of a medic does not come
through my office. That's done uh
through the administration, what have
you. But it was something that a mistake
a step had had been missed of getting
budget. Um, as the mayor stated, I
believe former Chief Mafen when he saw
that budget got confused or that he saw
that money and thought he had done a
step, which those were for the previous
two medics he had done and he just saw
that money and thought, "Oh, I got the
money for that." So, it's something that
the budget was there to make those
expenditures in 2023 and here we are in
2025 and um Chief Schultz caught that we
don't have anything for this one. So,
and we're here now because it wasn't um
budgeted for back in 2023 to get a
purchase order.
>> Council member Tiner. So the other
question I have is, you know, all the
debacle that had happened last year with
the fire department and that with the
money not being appropriated where it
should line item wasn't transferred and
I brought all this up when you talked
about buying the building uh building a
building for $600,000
and I asked you
then
is there anything else? Because what I
am finding out from people I'm talking
to is that when you order a medic, you
find out they send you an email and get
with you about when the frame's built,
when this is done. They do every step.
So you didn't know that when this was
coming on when you asked for a $600,000
building.
So, at the time to do the legislation
for the building and we needed some
additional funds to complete the project
and um as I was watching the other parts
of the budget um no I I did not
recognize the lack of a PO for Horton
for 355,000. Um I was well aware as my
command staff um giving me routine
updates of when the truck got on the
line, when the chassis was pured. So
they do provide us updates like that. Um
it's the administration, the fire
department, um just monitors that
process. The the specifications and the
details on where the radios and antennas
and where the boxes are going to go are
handled by the the committee who's spec
all those vehicles. So they had more
day-to-day knowledge of it, but I was
well aware that there was a medic in
production for Lanster Fire Department,
but I had no idea it had not been paid
for yet.
Service safety director Woody had her
hand up.
>> I was going to say I could add to that.
>> Thank you, mayor.
>> The building has nothing to do with the
vehicle. It's different.
>> No, but it was the question I asked. Is
there anything else? Because all the
surprises we got last year about this
line item and that it I asked, hey, is
there anything else that we're going to
need to know? And that's what I'm
talking about.
>> Chief, when did you find out about the
issue? A week and a half. Two weeks ago.
>> Approximately two weeks ago. Yes, sir.
So, we didn't know about it. I would
also add the safety committee members,
the administration,
uh, the fire chief, the fire
administration,
all those people no longer work for the
city.
U,
>> well,
>> this happened in 2022.
>> We could throw in there, too. I mean, I
know that you had indicated that council
was aware of it. This is an all new
council as well. So those these folks
wouldn't have been aware of it either
because I don't think very many of them
were here from 2022. Maybe council
member Tiner, council member Skunover.
So I just wanted to throw that out too
so that we could put that
>> right. The point is the administration
has to present to the council in office
at the time. The council in office at
the time was presented this information.
>> So that's the only way you can do it,
right?
>> Yeah. and and the administration at the
time, they obviously knew it too, but
the they felt the information was the PO
was not obtained. The process the
information come from the podium was
accurate. Uh and I believe that Chief
Mafen felt it was accurate. I
>> we're going to make sure it doesn't
happen again. It won't happen. Um I'm
not aware of the Trish as the auditor.
Have you had this situation arise?
>> I'm sorry. Uh, no. This is the first
time of anything of this nature. We've
had smaller expenditures where someone's
done it. That's that's smaller nature.
>> Nothing at $350,000.
>> Okay. Service safety director Woody.
>> Thank you, President Porter. I just
wanted to uh quickly address uh
Councilman Krytes and Councilman Tiner's
questions about processes because I'm a
processes person and we actually worked
with Auditor Nettles this year to
make our budgeting process a little bit
better and the new upgrade that we have
in the analytics software where each
department enters their budget offers
they're called worksheets but it offers
line items um so that we can actually
see each line item of what's going to be
included in their budget. That wasn't
always done in the past. They didn't
always have that opportunity. So, from a
process perspective, that's when the
mayor and I and the auditor will be able
to see and work with the department
heads when they're giving us a cost. had
we had this worksheet back in 2022 2023
to see um the $563
$563,000 that worksheet would have been
very beneficial for us to see that oh
well that $563 is already committed to
these two medics it doesn't include that
third medic. So I think having these
worksheets where we can itemize what the
budget and what the anticipated
spendings are will definitely help us
prevent things like this in the future.
>> Thank you. Thank you,
>> Law Director Hall. I had a question. Um,
you indicated that that the chief had
signed the contract
>> and that your office had not seen it.
>> Correct.
>> And, um, have you been able to look at
the contract now?
>> I have.
>> And are there any objectionable
provisions that we would have had
removed from that contract had we been
able to look at it?
>> No, not necessarily. Um but it's it's
state law that you know the service
safety director is the one who signs for
the acquisition um that I also sign as
to review the form. Um and then I forgot
to mention the auditor's certificate. So
the auditor is also required to sign and
and recognize um that the city either
has the money in collection or has the
money in a fund uh ready to you know use
on the equipment that's being purchased.
So,
>> and then if we would do a then if the
council would choose to do a then and
now,
>> we would be covered for those things by
by taking this action.
>> By taking this action, you would be
approving, yes, the purchase. So, you're
just kind of doing it backwards. You
would be approving the purchase, but
then at that point, um, we could either
just go forward with the contract that's
signed or we could just sign another
one, um, quickly that actually conforms
to the law. Um but still take yes
delivery and and pay for the equipment.
>> Thank you.
>> Yep.
>> Any further question? Council member
Skunover.
>> Um I just wanted to get some
clarification. So this was on our desk
when we got here. Your current list of
vehicles.
>> Mhm.
>> So it says current list, but so
you said the new Medex replacing the
2016,
>> correct? And so the 2013 is the current
backup.
>> It is reserve
>> reserve. So what's happening to the 13
when it goes off?
>> The 13 will be the second backup and it
for us beneficial to have two backups,
one to cover front lines, special duty
events, etc. Um we will also there's the
Navastar ambulance. um once we acquire
this additional medic would would be put
up for city auction. So we will maintain
a fleet of six for front line and it's
usually the newest in the oldest out um
you know one less vehicle to take care
of but still giving us a a comfortable
cushion of reserve apparatus.
>> Okay. And then
>> yes
>> part two question. So all of these are
currently active or in reserve
>> correct? So there's
there's seven
there's seven explorers, a Tahoe, and
two trucks,
>> correct?
>> That are all current.
>> So those are
>> like seven explorers are being used
>> front line and um so I'll I'll go
through those real quick.
>> Thank you.
>> The two um pickup trucks, one is a
designated station truck. We used it to
go pick up hose. We we brought the boat
to the scene when we had a water rescue.
Um the other is the grass fighter unit
that's at station two. Um it replaced a
truck from I think the 1980s, 1970s. Um
the explorers, they're um two of the
explorers are the front line and the
reserve um battalion vehicles, command
vehicles that are outside outfitted with
the lights and sirens and those things
that are needed. Um the Tahoe is kind of
a step down third in line. Um it was
used during the flooding event. Our
second battalion um was able to take
command of additional scenes. As far as
the explorers, the um the fire chief,
the battalion chief of EMS um have
explores and then the fire prevention
inspectors and the community paramedic
unit um all use it for um their daily
work work travels.
>> Okay,
>> thank you.
>> That is correct. And um you know, I will
add and I think it's a a great
opportunity to kind of see also the cost
how they've went up exponentially.
um you know the equipment that we need
to get. Um so replacing it now at a at
today's cost is beneficial to us. And
then um the five-year strategic plan
that I tried to lay out a lot of these
future purchases so make sure
everybody's on the same page. Um I was
able to discuss some of the future
planned purchases. There are no four
explorers. There was I think one towards
the end of 2028 29 um to replace kind of
the backup. That was it. Um and then the
other other medic units included in
that. So I it it seems like we've had a
lot of and we have a lot of legislation
issues with buying these medics. Um but
as I we look back through the years, you
know, from our frontline units to the
oldest one in the fleet, they're all
closed in age. We have a 23, 22, 19, 16,
13, 10, 8. So for nearly 20 years, we've
been buying trucks one a year, once
every couple years. There is a gap.
Everybody remembers what happened in
2008 and 2011 um which kind of slowed
some of the purchase down but um no I
just appreciate the opportunity you
bring that up to kind of um lay that out
for the rest of council who as the
president point out weren't here when a
lot of these decisions were made but
we're following some of the the best
practices and I've inherited these best
practices um over the last two decades.
>> Okay.
So any further question?
>> So go ahead.
>> Yeah. Council member Lockenberg.
>> Um this uh fire impact fee
was it does it have a line item in our
2025 budget? And if so, what was it
earmarked for within the budget? And how
much how much money has been accumulated
in there in excess of what we're looking
to spend now? And is it earmarked for
anything?
Not earmarked for anything.
>> No, I'm sorry. Go ahead,
>> M. I think we have 125 for this.
>> They budgeted to to buy the C and some
of the equipment for the truck, just not
the truck itself.
>> The fire impact fee was budgeted to
>> 125,000 for the it's a self-loading C
and load system. Um so it was budgeted
in 25 for that expensive equipment. Um
to answer their part of your question,
sir, the fire impact fee in 2024
uh raised and I had a report from the
building department roughly $1.3
million. Um we spent 985 a few months
ago uh when you gave me the approval to
purchase a firet truck. At this time, we
have a a cash balance of over 1.1
million um including the incumbrances
um of the equipment, not including the
truck that we're asking for money for
this evening.
>> So, there's an additional we got 1
something million in there.
>> We're going to spend 3553
for this and another 125,000 for
>> it'll be closer to 100,000. I hope there
was some miscellaneous expenses built
into that, but if it's not spent, we'll
go back into the the carryover.
>> The 125,000 is already encumbered, so
it's already included in the balance.
>> It's already been taken off what we
currently our balance would be
currently. So, the only thing that's
additional coming out of that is the new
truck cost.
>> So, we've got 850 900,000 sitting there
and it's not earmarked for anything.
It's just there
>> for the use of the fire department for
various
>> fire impact only. So fire apparatus,
fire building u repair, fire equipment
purchase, fire impact only.
>> Okay.
>> So I have one final question, chief. If
if
>> worst case scenario, somehow or another,
Ven and now not approved, we're left
with this this medic that's been
customized to Lancaster's specs sitting
out there. How long would it take us to
to even get get one for ourselves if we
needed to then go back and put another
order in?
depending on the manufacturer and and
who we'd go with. Um, bill times are for
the the best that we can find currently
is 18 months. Okay.
>> And as we pointed out, this one's been
over two and a half years.
>> So, we could be looking two or two and a
half, three years.
>> Correct.
>> And as Director Hall alluded to, there
could be, and I don't want to put words
in the law director's mouth, but there
could be other consequences related to
that. So, um, so that could be the
outcome if that then and now was not
approved. So, all right. Thank you for
answering those questions.
>> Thank you, Mr. President.
>> Any further questions from council
members?
>> Hearing none, I think we're done with
this presentation. Thank you very much,
Chief.
>> You're welcome.
>> Petitions and memorials.
>> There are no petitions or memorials this
evening.
>> Thank you. At this time, we've reached
the time uh for permission of voters and
taxpayers to address council. Um it's a
threeminut rule and you have to sign in
on the um the sheet uh at the podium. Do
we have any individuals here who would
like to address council this evening?
Thank you.
>> My name is Jan Kosha. I live at 8:15
Lampton Circle in Lancaster. Good
evening, council and administrative
members.
I want to talk about a couple of things
that have been on my mind for a while.
Uh
back in June of last year, June 26th of
2024, there was a catastrophic house
fire on at 8:16 North Pierce Avenue.
That structure is sitting there today
just like it was the day they put the
fire out. And I would like to see some
movement to get that building demolished
and let's move on. It's it's a building
lot or whatever it turns out to be. And
in a little bit of research, I see that
the property was transferred to a local
LLC
about the end of May of this year. But I
don't know what impact that might have
on who's responsible now to tear that
structure down. Uh, as you all probably
remember, there was a three-year-old
child that perished in that fire. So,
every time you go by there, it's a
reminder of what that tragedy was all
about.
So, I'm hoping we can get some
action going to uh demolish that
building and
maybe somebody could build a new home
there.
Uh
the other thing I wanted to speak about
is railroad crossings in particular
three particularly the three railroad
crossings on the
west side that are traversed uh by the
most traffic. one being on Westfair
Avenue
uh near the stop
that's getting very bumpy there. It's
been fixed before and it seems to last a
few years. Uh the other is at Collins
Road
out toward uh 33
that if if you go over either of those
at the speed limit, you're going to
rattle your mers and
hurt your back a little bit, you know.
But the worst of these uh three
crossings that I'm talking about tonight
is on Edy Road. It is an absolute
disaster. You have to slow down to very
very slow 3 4 m an hour to cross that
without risking
getting damage to your vehicle.
And of course if you slow down to that
kind of speed, you got people behind you
that are upset.
But uh perhaps the city
can work with the railroads and get
something done with these crossings and
particularly on the EV road crossing.
And now that we're going to have a
firehouse right near there, it looks
like a good opportunity to not only fix
that crossing, but to fix the two
bridges and widen finally widen 80 road.
If you're going to have emergency
vehicles running up and down that that
road the way it is now, it's reached
you've reached your three minutes. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
Is there anybody else that wishes to
address council this evening? Hearing
none, uh, we thank you for coming.
>> We'll now move on to the reports of
standing committees.
>> I have eight of them. Um, I have
administrative services committee agenda
dated July 15, 2025 submitted by Mr.
Lockenberg. Water water pollution
committee agenda dated July 18, 2025
submitted by Mr. Wing. Economic
Development Committee Agenda dated July
22nd, 2025 submitted by Mrs. Hoop.
Safety Committee Agenda dated July 31st,
2025, submitted by Mr. Bishjack.
Economic Development Committee meeting
minutes dated August 2nd, 2025,
submitted by Mrs. Hoop. Water pollution
committee meeting minutes dated August
2nd, 2025, submitted by Mr. Wing. Law
Committee agenda dated August 10th, 2025
submitted by Mrs. Kates. Administrative
service committee meeting minutes dated
August 11, 2025, submitted by Mr.
Luenberg.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a
motion.
With my mic on, I'd like to make a
motion to receive and file the reports
of standing committees.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to receive
and reports of standing committees. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I. All those opposed same sign. Reports
of special committees.
>> I have none.
>> Thank you. No public hearing this
evening. So we will move on to the
reading of resolutions. We'll begin with
third reading of temporary resolution
5825.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the law enforcement
block grant jag grant police fund 2027
and approve a ven and now certificate
for purchases. This is through safety
committee Mr. Bisjack and Mrs. Tiner or
Miss Tiner, sorry.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass and engross upon the
written record temporary resolution
58-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
5825. Any discussion? Council member
Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This
legislation seeking to appropriate for
the UN unencumbered balance for the
amount of around $23,000.
Uh the money is coming from the JAG
grant uh funds for the purchase of body
cameras. This legislation is also
allowing uh passage for then announced
certificate to purchase these body
cameras uh with these funds.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler,
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Crates,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Lochner,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Mr. Sullie,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner, y
>> Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Temporary resolution passes 10 to zero.
Temporary resolution 5825 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary resolution 5925.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the DOJ equitable
sharing fund 2048 for grant match
dollars for the major crimes unit. This
again is through safety committee Mr.
Bisjack and Mr. Sully.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass and engross upon the
written record temporary resolution
59-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
5925. Any discussion? Council member
Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This money is
being appropriated from a shared asset
forfeite account for which uh is housed
with the major crimes unit but of which
the city of Lancaster is its fiduciary.
Um this money is being appropriated for
the purpose of providing a grant m uh
grant match um that the department of
justice uh is providing in the amount of
$40,000. Thank you. Any further
discussion? Hearing none, please call
the role.
>> Mr. ES, yes.
>> Mrs. Bler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kates, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Scott Scoover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Temporary resolution 5925 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary resolution 6025.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the 045 police and
fire levy 2021 or 2021 fund 2051 for the
purchase of four police vehicles for use
by the Lancaster Police Department.
Again, this is through safety committee,
Mr. Bisjack and Miss Teter.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. And I move
that council pass and engross upon the
written record temporary resolution
60-25.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion second to pass and gross
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 6025. Any
discussion? Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This
legislation is appropriating from the
unencumbered balance and is uh
addressing a purchase order error that
occurred in which uh funds were used to
pay for 2024 vehicles as opposed to 2025
cruisers. So, this is just addressing
that and uh reappropriating those funds
for uh the four 2025 cruisers coming up.
>> Thank Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Berler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. H.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Scoover,
>> Mr. Sie,
>> yes.
>> Miss Teamer, yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Temporary resolution 6025 passes 10 to
zero.
>> Temporary resolution 6125. A resolution
to schedule Lancaster City Council
meetings and finance committee meetings
for 2026. This is through law committee.
Mrs. Crates and Mr. Bisjack.
>> Council member Kates.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I would
like to make a motion that council pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record. Resolution temporarily numbered
61-25.
>> Second. A motion second to pass and
enter upon the written record. Temporary
resolution 6125.
Any discussion? Council member Kits. Uh
just briefly reminder this is uh
legislation to schedule council and
finance meetings for next year.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion
hearing? None. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Berler,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kes,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Spoonberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Teener,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wayne,
>> Temporary resolution 6125 passes 10 to
zero. We'll now move on to the second
reading of resolutions beginning with
temporary resolution 60-25
65-25.
>> A resolution to appropriate from the
undercumber balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor and the city income tax
fund 2016
to accommodate increase refunds in 2025
and to pay to pay and replace the backup
server for the income tax department
with a cloud-based system. This is
through finance committee. Mr. Skunover,
Mr. Sully.
>> Council member Skunover. It's a second
of three readings, please.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 65-25.
We'll now move on to the first reading
of resolutions, beginning with temporary
resolution 67-25.
a resolution authorizing the city
administration to act on behalf of the
city of Lancaster and enter into any and
all agreements or settlements necessary
to participate in new national opioid
settlements with Alvogen Inc. Amno
Pharmaceuticals Inc. Apotex Inc. Hikimma
Pharmaceuticals USA Inc. In Indiv
Indivor Inc. Milon
Stephanie, this is not very nice.
>> I'm very sorry.
>> Milon Pharmaceuticals.
>> Sorry.
>> Sun Pharmaceutical Industries
Incorporated and Zidus Pharmaceuticals
USA Incorporated and to declare an
emergency. There you go.
>> Thank you. I appreciate that.
>> You're welcome.
>> Council member Kits.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Uh, first of
three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 6725.
Please tune in. uh in two weeks to watch
the rereading of those names.
Temporary temporary resolution 6825,
>> a resolution to declare a continuing
real and present
emergency due to weather in the city of
Lancaster Law Committee. U Mrs. Crates
and Mr.
Scootover,
>> are we going to keep it?
>> Okay, Mrs. Ber.
>> Okay, thank you. Um, Council Member
Kits.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I would like
to make a motion that council suspend
its rules and wave the second and third
readings of resolution temporarily
numbered 67-25.
Nope, sorry, 68-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to suspend
the rules and we have the second and
third reading of temporary resolution
6825.
Any discussion? Council member Christ.
>> Just briefly, we're asking for
suspension. And this is related to the
recent flooding and emergency situation
where we would like to go outside of the
bidding process to get those um the FEMA
application and the um emergency issues
cleared up.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion
hearing? None. Please call the role on
the motion to suspend.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Bller, yes.
>> Mr. Bisj, yes.
>> Mrs. Kra, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> Mr. Scoover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes. Mr. Miss Tiner.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wing.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and we have
the second and third reading of
temporary resolution 6825 passes 10 to
zero. Council member Kits.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I would like
to make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Resolution temporarily numbered 68-25.
>> Second. We
>> have a motion a second to pass and gross
and enter upon the written record.
Temporary resolution 6825. Any further
discussion?
>> No, thank you. Hearing none, please call
the role.
>> Mrs. Mr. Eelss,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Berler,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Craig,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Skoonberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tinder,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Temporary resolution 6825 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary resolution 6925.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the general fund 10001
to accommodate sick leave and vacation
acral payouts for the retirement of the
Fairfield County Municipal Courts
Director of Probation Services and to
declare an emergency. This is through
finance committee Mr. Skunover and Mr.
Sully.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> Mr. Mr. President, I'd like to make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third readings
of temporary
resolution 6925.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, a second to suspend
the rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary resolution 6925.
Any discussion? Council member,
>> just we're asking for suspension at the
request of the auditor. So, this account
is in the red for Miss Bartekch's
retirement payoff. Thank you very much.
Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Berler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Luckenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second third reading of temporary
resolution 6925 passes 10 to zero.
Council member Skinner.
>> Mr. Mr. President, I'd like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
or resolution 6925.
>> Second have a motion and second to pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution 6925. Any
further discussion?
>> No. Thanks.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler. Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Luckenberg?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Skunover?
>> Mr. Sullie?
>> Yes.
>> Mainer? Yes.
>> Mr. Wing?
>> Yes. Temporary resolution 6925 passes 10
to zero. Temporary resolution 7025,
>> a resolution authorizing the ser service
safety director to enter in engineering
agreement for updating the division of
water asset management plan as required
by the Ohio Environmental Protection
Agency and Ohio Water Development
Authority. This is your water water
pollution committee control and Mr. Wing
and Miss Tener.
>> Council member Wing. Yes, this is the
first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 7025.
Temporary resolution 7125.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to advertise for a
request for qualifications and issue a
request for proposals for a design
professional for design and construction
administration of the Ed Road fire
station project and to declare an
emergency. This is through safety
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Sully.
Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This is the
first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 7125.
Temporary resolution 7225.
>> A resolution to increase receipts.
Appropriate from the unencumbered
balance. Amend the certificate of other
sources and appropriations with the
county auditor and the fire impact fund
3022.
Issue a then announced certificate for
the purchase of a new medic unit and
declare an emergency. This is through
safety committee. Mr. Bisjack and Miss
Tina.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council suspend its rules and wave the
second and third reading for uh the
resolution temporarily numbered 72-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to suspend
the rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary resolution 7225.
Any discussion? Council member Bisjack.
>> No, Mr. President.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> yes. Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> Mr. Wink,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
resolution 7225 passes 10 to zero.
Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. The resolution
temporarily numbered 72-25.
>> Second. We have
>> a motion second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record. Temporary
resolution 7225.
Any discussion? Council member Bisjack.
>> No, Mr. President.
>> Thank you. Uh, any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Bler,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Craigs,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Teener,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wing,
>> Temporary resolution 7225 passes 10 to
zero.
>> We will now move on to the reading of
ordinances, beginning with the third
reading of temporary ordinance 2825. an
ordinance declaring the improvement to
certain real property located in the
city of Lancaster, Ohio to be a public
purpose declaring such improvement to be
exempt from real property taxation
pursuant to Ohio Revised Code section
5709.40B
40B
requiring the owners thereof to make
annual service payments in lie of taxes.
Describing the public infrastructure
improvements to be made that will
directly benefit the real property.
Establishing a public improvement tax
increment
equivalent fund for the deposit of
service payments together with related
authorizations in declaring emergency.
This is through economic development
committee Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Kra.
Council member Hoop.
>> Yes, Mr. President. I'd like to make a
motion that council pass engross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 28-25.
Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record temporary ordinance 2825.
Any discussion? Council member Hoot.
>> Um yes, just briefly. This is the West
End city tip that we are voting on right
now.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion
hearing? None. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Betler,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kes,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wing,
>> Temporary ordinance 2825 passes 10 to
zero.
>> Temporary ordinance 2925.
>> An ordinance declaring the improvement
to certain real property located in the
city of Lancaster, Ohio to be a public
purpose. declaring such improvement to
be exempt from real property taxation
pursuant to Ohio Reise Code section
5709.40B
40B requiring the owners thereof to make
annual service payments in lie of taxes.
Describing the public infrastructure
improvements to be made that will
directly benefit the real property
establishing a public improvement tax
increment equivalent fund for the
deposit of service payments together
with related authorizations and declare
an emergency through economic
development committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mr.
Skinner.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Um yes, Mr. President, I'd like to make
a motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record. Um,
temporary ordinance 29-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record. Temporary ordinance 2925. Any
discussion?
>> U, this is the same legislation as the
prior, but this is just the east end
tiff.
>> Thank you. Um, hearing no further
discussion, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Mrs. Kra.
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> Mr. Mr. Luxenberg.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Skenover.
>> Mr. Sullie.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> Mr. Wink.
>> Yes.
>> Temporary ordinance 2925 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary ordinance 30-25.
>> An ordinance declaring the improvement
to certain real property located in the
city of Lancaster, Ohio to be a public
purpose. declaring such improvement to
be exempt from real property taxation
pursuant to Ohio Revised Code section
5709.40B
requiring the owners thereof to make
annual service payments in lie of taxes
describing the public infrastructure
improvements to be made that will
directly benefit the real property.
establishing a public improvement tax
increment equivalent fund for the
deposit of service payments together
with related authorizations in declaring
emergency through economic development
committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Kurtz.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> U Mr. President, I would like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 30-25.
Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to pass
and gross an owner upon the written
record temporary ordinance 30-25.
Any discussion, council member?
>> Um yes, just briefly. This is the third
and last um it's the central tiff and
it's
um including four different sites. Cells
green site, the Fairfield shoe
um right on Columbus Street, Fairfield
Metro Park again on Columbus Street, and
then the reserve at Hunter Trace.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Berler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Temporary ordinance 30-25 passes 10 to
zero. Second reading of ordinances
beginning with temporary ordinance 3125.
An ordinance to amend the Lancaster
codified ordinances part 11 planning and
zoning title three zoning and property
re restrictions and to adopt chapter
short-term rentals. This is through code
enforcement and zoning committee Mr.
Sully and Mrs. Hoot. Council member
Sulli.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This will be
the second of uh three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 31-25.
Temporary ordinance 32-25,
>> an ordinance to accept the annexation of
0.605
plus or minus acres in the Pleasant
Township and to declare an emergency.
This is through economic development
committee, Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Kates.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the third reading of temporary ordinance
32-25.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion. Second to suspend the
rules and wave the third reading of
temporary ordinance 3225. Any
discussion?
>> No. Thank you.
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Betler,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Screenover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sullie,
>> Miss Tiner, yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary ordinance
3225 passes 10 to zero.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Mr. Mr. President, I'd like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 32-25.
Second motion a second to pass gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 3225. Any further discussion?
Council member Hoop.
>> No. Thank you.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Bler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Teener,
>> And Mr. Wing.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary ordinance
3225 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
ordinance 3325.
>> An ordinance to a excuse me to amend the
zoning map subject to passage of the
annexation of 0.605 plus or minus acres
in the Pleasant Township and to declare
emergency. Mr. Economic Development
Committee, Mrs. Hoop and Mr. Wing.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the third reading of temporary ordinance
33-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion second to suspend the
rules. Wave the third reading of
temporary ordinance 3325. Any
discussion? Council member who?
>> No.
>> Thank you. Uh, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Bller,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. K,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. H,
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tanner,
>> yes. And Mr. Wing.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary ordinance
3325. Passes 10 to zero. Council member
Hoop.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council passing and gross and enter
upon the written record. Temporary
ordinance 33-25.
>> Second.
>> A motion second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record. Temporary
ordinance 3325. Any discussion?
>> No. Thank you.
>> Hearing none, please call the RO.
>> Mr. Ess.
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Berler.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Price.
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Luenberg.
>> Mr. Skoover.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> Yes.
>> And Mr. Wing.
>> Temporary ordinance 33-25 passes 10 to
zero. First reading of ordinances
beginning with temporary ordinance 3625.
>> An ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance 54-24,
the non-UN pay ordinance, and to declare
an emergency. This is through code
enforcement and zoning committee. Mr.
Sully and Mr. Luckenberg. Council member
Sie.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This uh
legislation is to add a a new zoning
inspector. This will be the first of two
readings.
>> Thank you.
Temporary Ordinance 3725,
>> an ordinance to establish new permanent
rightofway along a new center line in
connection with the Arbor Valley Drive
rehabilitation project
to vacate the existing Arbor Valley
Drive rightway once the new Arbor Valley
Drive
Arbor Valley Drive rightway is dedicated
and to and acquire an new easement for a
water man in connection with the new
Lancaster High
Suit public works committee Miss Tiner
and Mr. Als
>> Council member Teen
>> first of three readings
>> first of three readings on temporary
ordinance 3725
temporary ordinance 3825
>> an ordinance amending part five general
offenses
code of the Lancaster codified ordinance
and adopting chapter 568 camping
prohibited um this is through law
committee Mrs. Kates and Mrs. Council
member Crates.
>> Yes. First of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 3825.
Temporary ordinance 3925.
>> An ordinance to grant to an ordinance to
grant to South Central Power Company it
successors and assigns a franchise for
the right of to acquire, construct,
maintain, and operate in the streets.
Their fair their
>> their affairs.
>> Their affairs. I'm sorry. Alleys,
bridges, and public places of the city
of Lancaster, Ohio, and his successors
lines for the transmission and
distribution of electric energy to the
city of Lancaster and the inhabitants
there thereof for lights, heat, power,
and other purposes. And for the
transmission of the same within,
through, or across said city of
Lancaster, and to declare an emergency.
This is through law committee, Mr.
Bisjack and Mr. Skuniver.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This will be
the first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 3925.
It appears that we have reached the
agenda for our legislation this evening.
Uh we have no tabled legislation. Um any
unfinished business?
Hearing none, we'll move to new
business. Uh tonight's agenda, we will
have brief committee updates from
committee chairs. We're just going to go
around the room. If you don't have an
update, you can just tell us when your
next meeting is. If you don't know, you
can say pass. Um, council member who
>> economic development
>> too soon. I was going to look up I think
my next committee meeting is sometime in
October.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> But it'll before the next council
meeting, but I have no updates.
>> Okay. Thank you very much. Um, Council
Member Wing.
>> Yeah. Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. Uh
our committee is very busy and has a lot
going on. So I'll keep it brief and
maybe just present a couple things.
>> So make sure you tell us what your
committee is
>> at each meeting. Yes, it's the water and
water pollution control committee.
>> Thank you.
>> Um I'll just talk about the three
biggest projects we've been discussing
quite a bit our committee meetings. Um
happy to report that uh phase two of
Upper Hawking is up and running. Uh the
north water plant is coming along very
nicely and at our last committee uh we
were informed that um we are still right
on target for the October 1st completion
date and um many folks especially on the
east side of town have probably been
interrupted by the um or inconvenenced
by the sewer separation project on on
Main Street there by Cherry Street and
uh that is still progressing and will be
completed by November.
>> Thank you. Thank you very much. Council
Member Bitler, we're gonna skip you
because you've just got here.
>> Thank you.
>> You're quite welcome. And we need to get
you a chair. Did they give you the worst
one?
>> Well, it's just that my legs are so
short and I have nothing to put my feet
on. My this low.
>> Typically, typically the practice is
that they give give the new person the
worst chair. I sat at a meeting that I
barely had my head over.
>> We didn't do that when I was president
of council.
>> I know. I'm I'm falling down. We need to
get you a stool. I'm falling down.
We're We're happy you're here. Uh
Council Member Skoonover.
>> Um with finance, I mean, everybody
attends all of the finance meeting
minutes or meetings. Hopefully everybody
is okay with the new agenda. I kind of
threw that at you to, but it's just to
kick it straight to you so you can
hopefully you're prepared. So, I'm gonna
throw the mayor on the spot. he doesn't
have to answer, but we did have
conversation about and hopefully with
you in your next committee meetings your
and you'll probably want to get with
them beforehand. Your um superintendent
of your departments should have like
should have updated year-to-ate budget
sheets for you. So when you're talking
about new legislation, you should be
able to say, "Okay, you're telling me
it's coming out of this fund. Let's look
at this fund." And you guys should be
able to discuss it. So you're a little
more in tune with what they're asking
for before they come and talk to us here
as a whole. So that's what I got.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Council member Tiner, public works.
>> Yes. And uh it isn't on the agenda on
here, but we do have a meeting next
month uh on the 12th on a Friday at
7:30. We have ours every other month.
So, we will have one. Um I was told by
Kurt that next month, one of the reasons
why we're also having a meeting, uh
they'll be going over the streets for
next year. So, they'll be picking those.
Um uh mosquito fogging, I don't know if
anybody's up late to see that. It starts
at 1000 p.m. and ends at 6. Um, now at
that time back in July, it was from 900
p.m. to 1:00 a.m. Um, the uh cemetery,
they paved the roads at Maple Grove that
is finished and they' worked on
maintenance buildings and that. So, and
then the school things are are moving
along. And I want to address
um Jan um about that house. Um I'm going
to go ahead and just do it now. um that
has been a work in progress and it has
been very hard on me
with the memorial that was outside for a
long time and I would get people calling
you know some people wanted it to stay
some people didn't it was very hard
because it was there for months it was
rained on there were bugs and it was
this has been a very hard one because
also there's a there was an issue with
the owner also so it has been a work in
progress I even got with the health
department. Um
it it has been really hard for a lot of
people and I worried about the
neighbors. I had even volunteered to get
a big
um bin and go pick up the animals that
were there, you know, the stuffed
animals and get them to the family. It's
just been a very hard thing to deal with
and and I know the city's deal has dealt
with it. Zoning's dealt with it. um code
enforcement, health department. The
health department didn't have anything
about an, you know, stuffed animals.
There's all kinds of things out there
about all kinds of other structure, but
like there was nothing about stuffed
animals. I mean, it was and that was
kind of a hard thing because, you know,
we all go by on the roads and we see
little memorials and that and so that
did get cleaned up. So, but it is being
worked on.
>> Thank you for your update. We'll now
move on to Council Member Kates.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. Uh the
law law committee meeting is next coming
up this Friday um at 9:00 a.m. at the
1897 conference room. We will have a
potential uh guest speaker um covering
marijuana dispensaries. We're also going
to take a look at um some new um issues
that have come up, which is fees
collected for public improvement
inspections, and we're looking at um
combining uh into one inspector and
having those fees be allocated toward
that single inspector for efficiency
reasons. Um, and then also we're going
to be discussing the uh conflict between
the city's parking ordinance and the
traffic code for residential streets and
our new zoning code for the um parking
of commercial vehicles in residential
areas.
>> Thank you, Council Member Crates.
Council member Als. Uh yes, I chair the
service committee and if you remember
last month I got a little excited about
the lack of activity at Bowowers Park
and I'm happy to report that there is
activity at Bowers Park. As of last
week, uh, they're moving dirt at the
Ohio engineers, who have not been there
that I know of for at least six months,
maybe a year, showed up miraculously
last week, and they're moving dirt. So,
I'm happy to report that. I don't just
pick on the parks department. I
>> That's my job. And I'm also, thanks to
Amanda, uh, I'm part of the, uh, Friends
of the Parks. I'm I'm on the board and
they asked me to make pancakes this
weekend. So, if you're hungry, Saturday
morning, I'm making pancakes.
>> Where?
>> At the fairgrounds. All right.
>> Part of the tractor show. I'm not part
of the tractor show. I'm making
pancakes. Okay. I have no tractors.
>> Thank you for that clarification.
>> Yes. Thank you, Council Member
Luckenberg.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I chair the
administrative services committee uh
which includes the IT and GIS
departments, the HR department, the SSD
uh city facilities manager as well. And
uh we uh out coming out of it, we've got
four new tornado sirens that are going
to be installed at the end of August,
early September. Uh, as Justin spoke
about earlier, we've had uh cyber
training of city employees. They're also
working with the police department on
their 911 upgrade. So, that's kind of
exciting. Coming out of it and coming
out of the uh SSD area, the city hall,
as you can see, the renovation pro
project has begun. Full steam ahead.
>> Thank you.
>> Yep. Another gentle reminder, council
members, take your cyber security
training.
>> We are in the 10%.
Thank you. Um,
Council Member Bisjack. Uh, thank you,
Mr. President. I chair the safety
committee meeting. Uh, and we just had
our safety committee meeting literally
last Friday. Uh, so just to provide a
light recap what happened there. Um,
Langster Police Department currently is
looking to uh pursue a school resource
officer contract with the Langster City
Schools, but nothing concrete on that
yet. It could potentially lead to five
additional officers being hired, but
once again, I want to emphasize there's
a lot of variables at play here um
before that uh before any kind of
commitment like that can be made
official and solidified. Uh,
additionally too, uh, HVAC has finally
been installed. It's running. It's
working. I did a ride along last
Saturday. Uh, feels great in there. So,
I'm glad our officers and everybody are
no longer sweating um in our police
department building there. Uh,
additionally, our Axon camera fleet
system has been installed in all of our
marked cruisers. Uh, moving on to the
Langster Fire Department. Uh, the
auxiliary building out by engine house 3
has been delayed due to the large
amounts of rain um that have been uh
that have occurred over the last couple
weeks, but is still progressing. Um we
just you know introduced legislation for
hiring an architect for engine house 2.
So not much to add there. Uh
additionally too EMS billing uh is
moving smoothly so far. I believe it's
collected $1.1 million if memory serves
me correctly which has been returned to
the general fund. Uh so we're good on
that front. And then legislatively the
only update I have and this is more for
the 2026 budget not so much for the
safety committee. Um, but there is
another medic that the city's
potentially looking to purchase, but
that is going to be included in the 2026
budget, at least from what was shared
with the safety committee. So, that's
all I have. Thank you. Our next meeting
is October 10th. Thank you, Council
Member Sie.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I chair the uh
code enforcement and zoning committee.
Uh the two biggest things that we've had
here this year are our short-term rental
u adding uh legislation for short-term
rental codes for Airbnbs and you know
similar type properties. Something that
we'd been missing in the past. Um also
we we're adding a position for a zoning
inspector because our folks have been
very very busy uh with the amount of
develop growth and development we have
in our community. uh
you know they're really struggling to
keep up. So
>> that's all I have.
>> Thank you very much. Uh liquor license
permit.
>> We have a liquor license permit that we
received um for roosters permit number
07511421.
Low director Hall, do you would you like
to
>> Sure. So, um, the chief of police, as
soon as he gets one of these now, he
asks, um, somebody in his department to
do a CAD search and determine, um, you
know, what kind of activity is occurring
at the address. Um, and this is roosters
on Memorial Drive. Um, lots of calls,
but the majority of them not anything to
do with roosters. Um, traffic crashes in
the parking lot, um, officers pulling
people over in front of that location,
that kind of thing. There were only two
real calls for service at the business.
Um, and they were both just the patrons
irresponsibly
um holding their alcohol as as the chief
said, irresponsibly um being patrons, I
guess. Um, and that was it. So, I don't
think um we have any public safety
concerns uh to worry about with regard
to the the renewal of their permit and
and that's all we've got. We've got
until I think the 25th to get the the
return done. So
>> So, can we just take a motion and a
second for renewal?
>> Voice vote. Yep. It's fine.
>> Okay. Thank you. Um, could I have a
>> a motion for renewal from council member
Tiner?
>> Second from council member Skunover.
>> All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. There we
go.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you very much. Announcement of
scheduled meetings.
>> I have two. August 25th, 2025 at 6:30
p.m. here in council chambers and
September 8th, 2025 at 6:30 p.m. at
council chambers.
>> Thank you. We have no special meetings
scheduled. Regularly scheduled committee
meetings.
>> I have for this month law committee
August 15th at 9:00 a.m. City Hall 1897
conference room. Water water pollution
control service committee meeting at
August 18th at 7:30 a.m. City Hall 1897
conference room.
>> Thank you. Reading of bills.
>> I have two. One for um are there both
for MNCO $58.60
and $7063.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
we pay the bills.
>> Second.
>> A motion and second to pay the bills.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I. Those opposed, same sign. No need for
an executive session. I'll entertain a
motion to adjurnn.
>> Mr. President, I would like to make a
motion that we adjourn.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion, a second to adjurnn. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I. I.
>> Thank you. If you have legislation this
evening, please stay and sign your
legislation. Thank you.
>> Okay.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 740-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
>> Hi, this is Jill Henwood with the
Victoria Players Children's Theater in
Baltimore. We are currently in our
eighth season thanks to local support.
This month, we are really excited to be
chosen as a recipient of the Buckeye
Cares program. That means Buckeye will
make a generous donation to help our
efforts with every vehicle they sell
this month. From all of us at Victoria
Players Children's Theater, we say thank
you, Buckeye.